Edward Palmer manuscripts, 1861-1889
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Edward Palmer manuscripts, 1861-1889
AZ 197
Palmer, Edward, 1831-1911
This collection includes original manuscripts concerning Native Americans, Arizona military posts, and journeys in the Southwest. Holograph manuscripts in various hands include observations of Apaches while stationed at Camp Grant, 1866-1867; life and events at Camp Lincoln (Camp Verde), 1865-1866; observations made while living among the Pima Indians, 1885; Yuma Indians, 1867, 1885-1889; a journey from Fort Mohave to Williams Fork copper mines, 1870; a journey from Prescott to La Paz, 1869; Montezuma Well, ca 1866; and Civil War notes, 1861-1866.
.4 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Edward Palmer was an Acting Assistant Surgeon in the U. S. Army, and was later employed by the U. S. Dept. of Agriculture from 1865-1889. He was an amateur ethnologist, anthropologist, geologist and meteorologist.
Organization
This collection is organized into three series:
Series I: Apache and Camp Grant Material, 1866-1867
Series II: Life at Camp Lincoln (Camp Verde), 1865-1866
Series III: Miscellaneous Material, 1861-1889
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes original manuscripts concerning Native Americans, Arizona military posts, and journeys in the Southwest. Holograph manuscripts in various hands include observations of Apaches while stationed at Camp Grant, 1866-1867; life and events at Camp Lincoln (Camp Verde), 1865-1866; observations made while living among the Pima Indians, 1885; Yuma Indians, 1867, 1885-1889; a journey from Fort Mohave to Williams Fork copper mines, 1870; a journey from Prescott to La Paz, 1869; Montezuma Well, ca 1866; and Civil War notes, 1861-1866.
Access Terms
Apache Indians -- History -- 19th century
Pima Indians -- History -- 19th century
Military bases -- Arizona -- History
Fort Verde (Ariz.) -- History
Fort Verde (Ariz.) -- History
Fort Grant (Ariz.) -- History
Montezuma Well (Yavapai County, Ariz.) -- History
Arizona -- History -- To 1912 -- Sources
Arizona -- Description and travel
Holographic Manuscripts
Container List
- Series I: Apache and Camp Grant Material, 1866-1867
  - Camp Grant Material. 1866-1867 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Details of military interaction with the Apaches observed while Edward Palmer was stationed at Fort Grant. Observations includes the military defense of the Guido Igles Treaty, Indian Ration Day at Camp Grant, personal impression of the effect of the military on the Apaches and remarks made by Col. Chittenden to the Apaches at a preliminary meeting on March 31, 1867.
  - Apache Material. 1866-1867 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes Edward Palmer's observations of Apache courtship, marriage, adultery, dress, dancing and other customs.
- Series II: Life at Camp Lincoln (Camp Verde), 1865-1866
  - Arizona Notes. 1865-1866 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes three pencil sketches and notes about Camp Lincoln, and excursions taken to the Clear Creek Ruins, Beaver Creek, etc.
  - Camp Lincoln and Camp Verde. 1865-1866 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Describes life at Camp Lincoln which was moved to a new location on the Rio Verde River and became known as Camp Verde. Included are descriptions of Apache attacks, commissary prices, information about military companies stationed at the fort, meteorological notes, etc.
- Series III: Miscellaneous Material, 1861-1889
  - Pima Indian Material. 1885 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Cultural observations made be Palmer while he was living with the Pima Indians in 1885. This includes descriptions of "witchery," Indian doctors and their cures, construction of homes and burial customs.
  - Montezuma Well. 1866? (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Description of Montezuma Well on Beaver Creek with a pencil drawing.
  - Arizona War News. 1861-1866 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes original army orders.
  - Trip from Fort Mohave to Williams Fork Copper Mines. 1870 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Yuma Indian Material. 1867, 1885-1889 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Describes Yuma Indian customs including dress, the availability of temporary wives for guests, food and burial customs.
  - Trip from Prescott to La Paz. 1869 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes notes on the killing of Indians near La Paz.